hello welcome to another video of cod
snippet let's get started with spring
data jpa so in this spring boot playlist
we have covered lot of things lot of
basic concepts we have covered we have
covered most of the annotations and
Concepts like spring aop and
transactions now it is time to jump to
database connectivity side right so you
have application you need some kind of
database right so that is when spring
data jpa comes into picture in this
video we are going to have kind of a
introduction of spring data jpa so
without wasting any time let's get
started so this is going to be a fun
video so sit back relax and enjoy the
show so let's just go back and let's see
this diagram right this might be a
familiar diagram of most of you right
because I have covered this particular
diagram in one of my video when we saw
layered architecture initially right now
when we were looking into layer
architecture we saw that inside our
spring boot application we have this
controller layer service layer and
repository layer right now whenever we
play along with some kind of data or
object data inside our application we
need need some kind of database to store
it right we need some kind of database
to hold that data right because each
time when you reload your application
the data that you store locally inside
your project will be scrapped right you
will not be able to retain that so the
basic use case is basically database
right we all know this until now in this
series we have made use of H2 database
right and we have done a lot of database
operations as well but we haven't looked
into string data jpa Basics yet now when
your repository layer is talking to
database base now whenever your
repository layer is talking to your
database there should be some kind of
connectivity between these two right
there should be some kind of
connectivity between your Java
application and your database right
database can be anything right it can be
SQL database it can be H2 database it it
can be any nosql database like couch
base or it can be any Cloud database
like Dynamo DB right there should be
some kind of connection between your
repository layer and your database that
is your spring application and your
database right now let's go back and T
time and let's see the traditional way
of doing this so if you build any
traditional application without spring
boot framework then still you will be
able to connect to database right still
you'll be able to connect to this
particular database through your Java
application now how they used to do it
they used to do it by something called
as jdbc right jdbc that is Java database
connection right now when it comes to
Java database connection you will be
able to connect to your database by
using few simple steps right so these
are basically the steps that you need to
take right first you will need to load
drivers right so there will be some kind
of jdbc drivers that you need to load
after that you need to establish a
connection between your database by
using classes like driver manager right
after that you need to create SQL
queries right you'll need to create kind
of a query inside your Java application
you need to prepare a statement so there
will be something called a statement and
prepared statement you'll need to
prepare it according to your use case
right you need to actually write a
queries at insert into table name then
values and blah blah blah like that
right so here another language comes
into picture right I'm talking about SQL
in this case you'll need to actually
write a queries when you prepare a
statement right after that that query
might need some parameters so you have
your object right you have your entity
or object those entity must be mapped to
this query right and those parameters
needs to be set right so you need to
write a lot of code in order to do that
and at the end after this step you have
the option to execute your query that
will actually hit that query on that
respective database and insert your data
or take the data from the database right
basically crude operations right nothing
else now when spring framework came into
picture there is something called as
spring jdbc that came into picture right
now this is a framework which automate
lot of these things for you right but
it's still a jdbc connection but it will
automate this boiler plate code for you
right so I'm talking about this spring
data jdbc right so this will automate a
lot for you but it is still not jpa
right so we are moving in a direction of
jpa now right now after that we need to
understand the concept of om right what
exactly is orm om is basically object
relational mapping the term itself
defines what exactly it is right the
relationship between your object your
Java object or the object inside your
objectoriented programming it can be any
programming right and the relational
database that you have for example SQL
right so it's a mapping between your
object and relational database now when
you are defining your Java object your
Java object will have some kind of
fields right let's say if you're talking
about user you will have user ID
username email ID age and blah blah blah
right lot lot more things you will have
right now user is your kind of table and
the field inside it will be The Columns
of the table right so ID name user like
that right for example you have this
table you have the user ID and you have
the username so it looks kind of a
direct mapping between your this
particular object and this table right
isn't it at the end what you are going
to do you are going to perform crude
operations only right why we need to do
all these things right why we need to
establish connection blah blah blah blah
why the mapping cannot be a direct with
your object so that is when orm comes
into picture it will provide the direct
mapping between your entity or your
model or your Java object with your
table right for example example if you
go to code let me just zoom it a bit if
you go to your code you will be able to
see that there is a book object book
will have ID title author and genre
right now these can be direct columns
inside your table and your table can be
book right so this object to this
particular table mapping is basically om
right now in Java the object can be
anything right now for that particular
object the respective table should be
created inside your database right the
entries should should be added inside
your database automatically right the
data should be retrived the data should
be updated and deleted now how these
operations are going to happen right who
is going to take care of creating this
table who who is going to retrive the
data who is going to update delete the
data inside this table who is going to
manage all these things right who is
going to manage that is when Frameworks
comes into picture who is going to
automate all of these things for us
right now the famous framework for om is
hibernate you might have heard hibernate
name many times right so you have
different kind of Frameworks basically
hibernate is one of them we have
hibernate we have Eclipse link we have
open jpa right we have many Frameworks
right now most famous is basically
hibernate if you need to use or
somewhere you can go with hibernate this
is a very good framework it's basically
object relational mapping framework
right now that is om and hibernate for
us now let's go ahead and discuss jpa
what exactly is jpa jpa is basically
Java persistence API now jpa is not a
framework jpa is not a framework like
cybernet jpa is basically a
specification jpa is basically
specification provided by Java in order
to manage relational data inside your
Java application by using objectoriented
programming principles right this is
kind of a specification provided by Java
in order to manage relational data
inside your spring application ations
right now again this is not a framework
this a set of interfaces or we can say
set of guidelines right this needs a
implementation right this needs
implementation right what is the
implementation implementation is again
hibernate so hibernate is basically
implementation of persistence API Java
persistence API as this is a
specification this is not an interface
this guy will need kind of a
implementation right so iberet is
basically implementation of jpa right
and in turn jpa is basically using jdbc
in order to do database connection right
so it is kind of a hierarchy right jpa
internal uses hibernate and jdbc like
that now you may have question why do we
exactly need jpa and why not hibernate
right if jpa is internally using
hibernate why not to use it directly
right you can use no one is stopping you
right but in case if you need to migrate
away from hibernate then you will need
to do hell lot of changes inside your
application because jpa is kind of a
standard practice right everyone is
using it right it is kind of abstraction
layer on top of your hibernate right it
is simplifying stuff for you it is a
standardized API and works with
different providers like hnet is one
kind of one provider there may be any
other provider right JPI is basically
standardized API which can work with
many other providers like hibernate you
can use anything else as well now this
is basically jpa right now when it comes
to Spring data jpa right this is
different from this jpa spring data jpa
is basically framework provided by your
spring framework right in order to do
your database connections right if you
go ahead and check this now then you
have your spring boot application right
you have your spring boot application
and this is basically jpa right if you
see over here spring data jpa is kind of
a layer of abstraction on top of your
jpa right it's a layer of abstraction
which will provide you a lot of
interfaces okay you can directly make
use of those interfaces inside your
application you don't even need to
provide the implementation because the
implementation is handled by jpa and
hibernate internally right now spring
data jpa is abstraction which uses jpa
and jpa we know that it needs a
implementation and implementation will
be hibernate in this case and hibernate
will in turn use jdbc and jdbc will do
database connections and manage
everything for you right so this is how
spring data jpa flow will look like
spring data jpa will make your crude
operations very easy as it's a layer of
abstraction on top of jpa right it
simplifies crude operations by providing
interfaces like crude repository jpa
repository and paging and sorting
repository right all these repositories
we are going to look into when we
actually implement this right there are
many things to look into when we
actually jump inside the implementation
of jpa right so that is something we are
going to look into the next video we are
actually going to make use of H2
database and make use of of spring data
jpa in order to do database operations
crude operations by using spring data
jpa right so this is basically quick
introduction of spring data jpa and this
is basically base of our next video of
implementation right so that's it for
this video if you don't want to miss
implementation video don't forget to
subscribe to code snippet share this
video with your friends so that they are
also aware of what exactly is spring
data jpa that's it for this video see
you in the next video